<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Sandstorm.io Blog</title>
		<description>Latest updates on Sandstorm.io</description>		
		<link>https://sandstorm.io</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Case Study: Sandstorm for journalists</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jason_nstar&quot;&gt;Jason Hernandez&lt;/a&gt; is a journalist who often covers sensitive topics like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nstarpost.com/17518/145186/a/updated-fbi-continues-to-operate-spy-planes-without-warrants-despite-federal-rul&quot;&gt;mass&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://nstarpost.com/17486/159855/a/update-2-cellphone-surveillance-used-on-black-lives-matter-protesters-at-fourth&quot;&gt;surveillance&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nstarpost.com/&quot;&gt;North Star Post&lt;/a&gt;. And given the nature of his work, he and his colleagues are justifiably concerned about the information security, not just between journalists and sources, but also drafts and storage of source materials. So, when Jason was visiting the SF Bay Area, he dropped by Sandstorm meetup to talk about the Sandstorm server he set up so he and his colleagues so that they can still enjoy the benefits of web applications, like real-time collaboration, while keeping control over their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cAzOL_eoMdQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lightning Talk: Jason Hernandez talks about how North Star Post uses Sandstorm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you using Sandstorm for your work? I’d love to hear more about how you’re using Sandstorm and share your story. Drop me a line at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:community@sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;community@sandstorm.io&lt;/a&gt; and tell me about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you in the Bay Area? Hope you can make it to the next Sandstorm meetup: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-SF-Bay-Area/events/231065150/&quot;&gt;RSVP here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or share your Sandstorm use case at local meetups in: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-Boston/&quot;&gt;Boston&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-NY/&quot;&gt;New York&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-Berlin/&quot;&gt;Berlin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-CH/&quot;&gt;Zurich&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-New-Zealand/&quot;&gt;Wellington&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-23-case-study-journalists</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-23-case-study-journalists</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Richard Caceres talks about designing open source apps</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;We had the pleasure of having designer, developer, and app author &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rchrd2&quot;&gt;Richard Caceres&lt;/a&gt; speak at our Sandstorm.io &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-SF-Bay-Area/events/229350176/&quot;&gt;meetup&lt;/a&gt; in San Francisco on March 24, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his talk Richard emphasized the value of free and open source software, he shared design principles that app authors should follow (to create a more cohesive user experience across apps), and he also demoed a newly updated version of his TextEditor app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Every app would benefit from allowing you to customize the CSS. I think that’s really important. In TextEditor, you can do that now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Watch Richard&#39;s full talk to hear more about:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What makes good free software&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why you should develop apps for Sandstorm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The importance of design for apps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples of successful open source design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visual guidelines for apps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New TextEditor features (like customizable CSS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/L1cIXBx7_4Q&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;You can follow the slides here:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/14l0BXCWRHb2oXbui4kAE9QdWpS1bQ8y2UqHVp7wGBpI/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=3000&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to his talk, Richard has also recently announced &lt;a href=&quot;http://rchrd.net/x-gui/&quot;&gt;x-gui&lt;/a&gt;, a library of web components for building consistent web apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/n4n49dkfyskmhcmg5h0mfzk4kjvce2jcs8ravr7y7uw9xs2pzghh&quot;&gt;Try out TextEditor&lt;/a&gt; for yourself and don’t forget to leave a review!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-16-designing-open-source</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-16-designing-open-source</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>How self-hosted analytics preserve user privacy</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Filippo Valsorda just published &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.filippo.io/self-host-analytics/&quot;&gt;an overview of why to use Piwik for web analytics&lt;/a&gt; instead of Google’s product. He reflects on the fact that he saw &lt;strong&gt;18% more pageviews&lt;/strong&gt; with Piwik compared to Google Analytics, seemingly because self-hosted analytics get past ad-blocking browser extensions. I want to reflect on the privacy implications of running your own analytics and explain the nuts and bolts of how Piwik runs on Sandstorm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what Piwik on Sandstorm looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2016-05-12-blog-post-piwik-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;piwik screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-a-web-analytics-service-works&quot;&gt;How a web analytics service works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a website (let’s say example.com) that that embeds Google Analytics’ Javascript tracking code, a web browser like Chrome takes the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download the HTML content of example.com.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notice a SCRIPT or IMG tag going to Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download the Google Analytics tracking code from Google, whose purpose is to  &lt;strong&gt;tell Google Analytics the URL of the page that included it.&lt;/strong&gt; One main purpose of web analytics is to see a chart of which pages are popular, so it stands to reason that if Google runs the analytics tool, Google needs to know what page is being viewed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google has a strong &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/&quot;&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;, and this information typically falls under the heading of “Information we get from your use of our services,” and I am personally OK with sharing this information with Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-people-like-staying-private&quot;&gt;Some people like staying private&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://w3techs.com/technologies/details/ta-googleanalytics/all/all&quot;&gt;W3Techs&lt;/a&gt;, more than 50% of all websites use Google Analytics. This has a somewhat surprising result: Google’s analytics service knows about a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; fraction of all web page visits. After all, any central analytics service can see the webpage visits for all the sites using it. They can even see traffic patterns that each individual site operator cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some web surfers want to keep their surfing information private. They may be OK with the site owner knowing that someone visited, but Google is not the site owner. They may see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2016/03/data_is_a_toxic.html&quot;&gt;data as a toxic asset,&lt;/a&gt; per Bruce Schneier. Many of them use web browser add-ons like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/privacybadger&quot;&gt;Privacy Badger.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a website operator, this puts you in a bind. If you want to use Google Analytics to get a graph of which pages are popular, you need to share your users’ surfing patterns with Google. Google doesn’t distribute Google Analytics as software you can run; they only run it as a central service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different way to do web analytics is to use software running on a server that you maintain. This is called &lt;strong&gt;self-hosting web analytics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to do that is to do what &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.filippo.io/self-host-analytics&quot;&gt;Filippo Valsorda said:&lt;/a&gt; run a Sandstorm server and &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/xuajusd5d4a9v4js71ru0cwj9wn984q1x8kny10htsp8f5dcfep0&quot;&gt;install Piwik from the app market,&lt;/a&gt; and copy-paste something into your website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, that’s possible with a few presses on a touchpad. Getting to that point involved some fascinating challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-share-an-api-token-you-cannot-see&quot;&gt;How to share an API token you cannot see&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One design goal of Sandstorm is that apps are &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/using/security-practices/#true-confinement&quot;&gt;confined.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; An app in Sandstorm never learns a URL that outsiders can use to reach it. That way, the app must rely on Sandstorm for access control, which means the “Share access” button can always show the users who has access. Sandstorm can provide one interface for granting and revoking access across all apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Piwik needs a way to show a URL that a website operator can embed into their website, so that website visitors can be tracked by Piwik!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get past this Catch-22, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zarvox&quot;&gt;Drew Fisher&lt;/a&gt; built a new Sandstorm feature called &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/developing/http-apis/#creating-an-offer-template&quot;&gt;offer templates&lt;/a&gt;. Piwik asks Sandstorm to show a templated message, and an IFRAME from Sandstorm appears with that token placed into the templated message. Drew’s Piwik package was the first to use it, and it’s become the most common way for apps on Sandstorm to create copy-pastable instructions for how to connect to their APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-to-make-ip-addresses-available&quot;&gt;When to make IP addresses available&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another obstacle was IP addresses. Piwik needs to know the IP address of visitors so it can create a visual map to show website operators where in the world their visitors come from.  However, we didn’t want every Sandstorm app to be able to collect this data without user intervention. Drew added a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sandstorm-io/sandstorm/blob/432be37489b210b19d9677f29befcd5c910a0f76/src/sandstorm/api-session.capnp#L28&quot;&gt;way for client-side Javascript to optionally share the user’s IP address&lt;/a&gt;, while keeping the defaults safe. I’ll quote him here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;notbig&quot;&gt;
Normally, we strip the remote address from requests, since most applications shouldn&#39;t need it.  However, for those that benefit from it (like analytics), clients can opt into passing their IP on to the backend by adding an &quot;X-Sandstorm-Passthrough: address&quot; header to their request.  This would be a privacy leak for WebSession, since the grain can give the client scripts which would send the header, but ApiSession requires a user action, so it&#39;s safe here.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the above, an ApiSession covers requests that come in via an app’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/developing/http-apis/&quot;&gt;HTTP APIs&lt;/a&gt; such as Piwik’s tracking system, and a WebSession covers requests that come in from the grain owner clicking around, such as a site owner viewing their statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enabling-the-community&quot;&gt;Enabling the community&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we finished, we had built a foundation that other apps could build upon. You can try &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/4mfserfc04wtcevvgn0jw27hvwfntmt8j468y3ma55kj8d5tj9kh&quot;&gt;Hummingbird,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mnutt&quot;&gt;Michael Nutt&lt;/a&gt;’s real-time analytics tool, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8kr4rvyrggvzfvc160htzdt4u5rfvjc2dgdn27n5pt66mxa40m1h&quot;&gt;Radicale,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/synchrone&quot;&gt;Aleksandr Bogdanov&lt;/a&gt;’s package that enables calendar and contact synchronization by combining a few tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to make an open source web app that anyone can self-host safely, start at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/developing/&quot;&gt;Sandstorm Developer Hub&lt;/a&gt;. Sandstorm supports any programming language or stack, like PHP or Meteor or Rust, that runs on Linux. You’ll find a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/vagrant-spk/packaging-tutorial/&quot;&gt;packaging tutorial&lt;/a&gt; and detailed information about offer templates. And if you just want to start using Piwik, &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/xuajusd5d4a9v4js71ru0cwj9wn984q1x8kny10htsp8f5dcfep0&quot;&gt;check it out on the app market.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/developing/&quot; class=&quot;linkbutton&quot;&gt;See Developer Hub »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-12-analytics-privacy</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-12-analytics-privacy</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sandstorm lets university IT be the hero</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Picture yourself running a university IT helpdesk. When professors come to you, you point to the
tech tools your colleagues have already deployed. It takes a long process to get something new
approved. You know that’s been limiting professors’ creativity, but you haven’t known what to do
about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one day, Sandstorm comes along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now educators are empowered to help themselves. They can make course websites with Ghost, teach
students how to typeset documents using ShareLaTeX, or create shared folders for classes using
Davros. They can even use GrooveBasin to set up a collaborative radio station for a music history
course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that happens on your Sandstorm server, running safely within the institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;can-you-help-spread-the-word&quot;&gt;Can you help spread the word?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Néna Nguyễn just finished designing a page with the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/go/education&quot;&gt;information educators need about Sandstorm&lt;/a&gt;. I’m writing because
I need your help reaching educators and technologists to share it with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you think of an IT staffer or professor who is wondering how to get access to a wider variety of
software available at their institution? If so, please send them a link to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/go/education&quot;&gt;https://sandstorm.io/go/education&lt;/a&gt;. I just sent it to the head
of IT at my alma mater’s CS department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they ask you about security or privacy, you can tell them that Sandstorm is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/install/&quot;&gt;self-hostable&lt;/a&gt; open source software, integrates with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/business&quot;&gt;LDAP/SAML single sign-on&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-29-security-track-record&quot;&gt;automatically mitigates 95% of security issues, before they are even discovered&lt;/a&gt;.
For more on Sandstorm’s security design, read our
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/using/security-practices/&quot;&gt;security practices documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-06-university-it-be-the-hero</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-05-06-university-it-be-the-hero</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sandstorm for Work Beta: LDAP, SAML, organization management</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Sandstorm is a great way to run open source collaborative productivity apps like document editors, task managers, chat rooms, file sharing, and more (54 apps and growing), all in one place. Lots of people – including us – use Sandstorm every day as part of doing their jobs. For example, right now I am composing this blog post in &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/fq057t4ek3yt96xsfje6c1wv61pkjkqm9hs1539x4jqxjwzdp7fh&quot;&gt;Dillinger&lt;/a&gt; running on &lt;a href=&quot;https://oasis.sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;Sandstorm Oasis&lt;/a&gt; (our hosting service), but many people choose to self-host Sandstorm on their own machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right; width: 283px; height: 221px;&quot; src=&quot;/images/business-ldap.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/business&quot;&gt;Sandstorm for Work&lt;/a&gt; makes self-hosted Sandstorm easier to integrate into a corporate environment. That means you can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrate with LDAP (including Active Directory) or SAML for single-sign-on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manage user groups and domains as whole units rather than inviting each user individually.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specify organization-wide access control policies, like “no sharing outside of the organization”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/business&quot;&gt;And more…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re in beta now, so not all features are ready yet, but once you’ve installed Sandstorm you’ll automatically receive updates as they become available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get started now, install Sandstorm and choose “Sandstorm for Work” during setup (or if you already have a server, look for the “for Work” tab in the admin settings). Sandstorm for Work is priced at $15/user/month, and currently we’re offering a 90-day free trial. (It’s still open source! More on that in a bit.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/install&quot; class=&quot;linkbutton&quot;&gt;Install Sandstorm »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;productivity-apps-large-and-small&quot;&gt;Productivity Apps Large and Small&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Sandstorm for Work, you can run apps similar to popular SaaS products, but keep your data in-house. For example, you can run &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/h37dm17aa89yrd8zuqpdn36p6zntumtv08fjpu8a8zrte7q1cn60&quot;&gt;Etherpad&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/a0n6hwm32zjsrzes8gnjg734dh6jwt7x83xdgytspe761pe2asw0&quot;&gt;EtherCalc&lt;/a&gt; instead of Google Docs, &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/m86q05rdvj14yvn78ghaxynqz7u2svw6rnttptxx49g1785cdv1h&quot;&gt;Wekan&lt;/a&gt; instead of Trello, &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/vfnwptfn02ty21w715snyyczw0nqxkv3jvawcah10c6z7hj1hnu0&quot;&gt;Rocket.Chat&lt;/a&gt; instead of Slack, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8aspz4sfjnp8u89000mh2v1xrdyx97ytn8hq71mdzv4p4d8n0n3h&quot;&gt;Davros&lt;/a&gt; instead of Dropbox. Once you have Sandstorm running, you can install each new app with a click – no need to create a new account on a new service, and no worry about whether that service is sufficiently private and secure. With Sandstorm, running apps in-house is actually &lt;strong&gt;easier&lt;/strong&gt; than using SaaS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even more interestingly, you can run apps on Sandstorm that aren’t available anywhere else, like Simon Vansintjan’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/c6zfftftrra9d4pdyuc1psew65ukqrjujvk20fac4zke1uasxv10&quot;&gt;Annotate&lt;/a&gt;. The idea behind Annotate is simple: upload an image, then annotate it with comments. We at Sandstorm use it to discuss UI and illustration mockups. Here’s me using it to comment on a slide deck we’re working on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;max-width: 500px; margin: 1em auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/news/images/annotate.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/annotate-small.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I love about Annotate is its simplicity: Simon wrote the whole thing in a couple weekends. And yet, it’s enough to be useful to design teams anywhere. No matter what Simon decides to do in the future, this app will never disappear, and you don’t have to trust Simon because your data stays on your server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annotate is just one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;54 apps and growing&lt;/a&gt; on our app market. By installing Sandstorm at your workplace, you get access to all of these at once, under a single login, and without giving up control of your data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;security-behind-the-firewall&quot;&gt;Security Behind the Firewall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float: right; width: 236px; height: 188px;&quot; src=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/images/why-finegrained.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you want to run apps on your own infrastructure, behind your firewall, you need to think about security. A malicious app – or a buggy app that gets hacked – can compromise your whole network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Sandstorm protects you. Sandstorm is the only container engine that implements &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/how-it-works&quot;&gt;fine-grained isolation&lt;/a&gt;, locking every document in its own container. By doing so, it prevents any app from compromising the server or network, and indeed &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/using/security-non-events/&quot;&gt;it renders 95% of app security vulnerabilities moot before they are even discovered&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;developing-for-enterprise&quot;&gt;Developing for Enterprise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you a developer of a web app aimed at enterprise? Do you ever get requests for an on-prem version, but find it hard to fulfill this request given the myriad environments and infrastructure you’d need to support? Perhaps we can help. If you target Sandstorm, then these logistics become our job. If your app works on one Sandstorm server, it will work everywhere. If you are interested in learning more, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/developer&quot;&gt;check out our developer features&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#105;&amp;#111;&quot;&gt;e-mail us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-it-open-source&quot;&gt;Is it Open Source?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes! Sandstorm for Work features are part of the same codebase as the rest of Sandstorm and under the same Apache 2.0 license. However, in order to unlock Sandstorm for Work features, we ask that you buy a “feature key” from us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does that work? Can’t anyone just remove the feature key check? In fact, yes, you can. However, if you did that, you would not be able to take advantage of our automatic updater, which ensures that your server is updated to the latest version within 24 hours of any release with no effort on your part. Automatic updates are important to keep your server secure and to make sure you can always run the latest apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purchasing a feature key also entitles you to priority support. However, we don’t want to be a company who primarily sells support, because we think that creates a perverse incentive for us to make our product hard to use. Indeed, it is our goal that no one should ever need to contact support at all, but under a support model, we’d be putting ourselves out of business! Under the feature key model, we are selling features, and promising support if there are problems. This way, we are incentivized to make sure there are no problems, because then we don’t have to answer support tickets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-future&quot;&gt;The Future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to release features early and often – we push a new release almost every week. What we are announcing today is only the beginning of what we have in store for Sandstorm for Work. Over the coming months, we’ll be adding features like group management (to make it easier to share documents with your team), audit logging (keep track of who has been accessing what, for security and compliance purposes), customizable access control policies, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you install Sandstorm today, &lt;strong&gt;you’ll automatically get these features as they become available&lt;/strong&gt; – your server will automatically update after every weekly release with no action needed on your part. So why not install now and see what you think? Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sandstorm-io/sandstorm/issues&quot;&gt;file a bug&lt;/a&gt; to tell us what you want to see next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;a style=&quot;display: inline-block; width: 250px; margin: 4px 0;&quot; href=&quot;https://demo.sandstorm.io&quot; class=&quot;linkbutton&quot;&gt;Try a demo »&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a style=&quot;display: inline-block; width: 250px; margin: 4px 0;&quot; href=&quot;/install&quot; class=&quot;linkbutton&quot;&gt;Install Sandstorm »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-04-06-sandstorm-for-work</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-04-06-sandstorm-for-work</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sandstorm&#39;s security track record, and what it means for self-hosting</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Today I want to share the results of our own &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/using/security-non-events/&quot;&gt;analysis of security issues of web apps available on
the Sandstorm app market&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;of-security-issues-automatically-mitigated-before-they-were-discovered&quot;&gt;95% of security issues automatically mitigated, before they were discovered&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandstorm automatically protects users from a huge fraction of the publicly disclosed security
vulnerabilities discovered in apps on the Sandstorm app market, before the vulnerabilities were even
disclosed. Of the issues we examined, 95% were wholly or partly mitigated. You can read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/using/security-non-events/&quot;&gt;full
report here in our
documentation&lt;/a&gt;. The analysis covers
publicly-disclosed vulnerabilities in Etherpad, WordPress, Roundcube, ShareLaTeX, and Tiny Tiny
RSS. In WordPress, we limited our analysis to security issues of severity score 6 or higher, due to
the large number of issues. We also mitigated 21 CVEs in the Linux kernel to prevent sandbox
breakout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built Sandstorm to create a &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2014-07-21-open-source-web-apps-require-federated-hosting&quot;&gt;viable ecosystem for indie and open source web
apps&lt;/a&gt;. When
server apps are as safe to run as apps on a phone, people will feel free to choose whatever software
they like. Consider that some Sandstorm apps, like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-25-giftr&quot;&gt;Giftr&lt;/a&gt;, are small and don’t have as many people
checking the code for bugs. Sandstorm protects you when you use those apps, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that security is risk-management, not binary. No software, Sandstorm included, will ever
protect all user data from all bugs in all programs. However, raising barriers to a successful
attack means fewer successful attacks will occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-hosted-apps-can-be-as-secure-as-a-centralized-web-app&quot;&gt;Self-hosted apps can be as secure as a centralized web app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Sandstorm, you get an experience as easy to use as software-as-a-service, and you retain the
privacy benefits of self-hosting. One of our key security strategies is to isolate each grain
(typically, one document) separately, so that a buggy or malicious app has a hard time ruining your
day. That degree of isolation is enabled by our various &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/how-it-works&quot;&gt;security
practices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you’ll &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/using/security-practices/&quot;&gt;read the full
analysis&lt;/a&gt;, prepared by myself and
Kenton Varda. &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/sandstorm-dev&quot;&gt;Let us know&lt;/a&gt; what
you think!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-self-hosting-is-secure-users-are-free-to-choose&quot;&gt;When self-hosting is secure, users are free to choose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security enables freedom of choice. If you use a Sandstorm server, you can choose productivity tools
that fit your needs, even if the server is maintained by someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to chat with colleagues? Install
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/vfnwptfn02ty21w715snyyczw0nqxkv3jvawcah10c6z7hj1hnu0&quot;&gt;Rocket.Chat&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/qkgkaxfqhgsff8zgx2f4nf1a8xvmpte6wa19egmfkk06mzt7e8dh&quot;&gt;Let’s
Chat&lt;/a&gt;. Want to
track tasks and stay organized? Install
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/m86q05rdvj14yvn78ghaxynqz7u2svw6rnttptxx49g1785cdv1h&quot;&gt;WeKan&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/0dp7n6ehj8r5ttfc0fj0au6gxkuy1nhw2kx70wussfa1mqj8tf80&quot;&gt;Simple
Todos&lt;/a&gt;. Want to
organize a gift exchange? Install
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/tr3w5p7ajsf61nf2e6dkfv8tdjes0qsm5w6ew0frd4qwnacwur90&quot;&gt;Giftr&lt;/a&gt;. Want to
share files quickly with friends? Install
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/nn7axgy3y8kvd0m1mtk3cwca34t916p5d7m4j1j2e874nuz3t8y0&quot;&gt;FileDrop&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8aspz4sfjnp8u89000mh2v1xrdyx97ytn8hq71mdzv4p4d8n0n3h&quot;&gt;Davros&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you prefer managed hosting, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://oasis.sandstorm.io/&quot;&gt;make an account on Oasis&lt;/a&gt; and
enjoy any of these apps or upload your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or you can run your own Sandstorm install. Over the past six months, we’ve integrated &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2015-10-01-free-ssl-certificates&quot;&gt;free SSL
certificates&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2015-09-24-is-curl-bash-insecure-pgp-verified-install&quot;&gt;cryptographically-verified automatic
updates&lt;/a&gt; into
self-hosted Sandstorm. As soon as someone installs Sandstorm for an organization, they can safely
allow colleagues to choose their own tools. If you install Sandstorm for yourself, you can use the
best indie web apps and let the platform handle security for you.  Get started on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/install&quot;&gt;Sandstorm
install page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-29-security-track-record</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-29-security-track-record</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Andrew Wansley shares his story of Giftr</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Giftr is one of the newest additions to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/&quot;&gt;App Market&lt;/a&gt;; it helps make coordinating gift exchanges less painful for you and other gifters involved. At our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-SF-Bay-Area/events/227595644/&quot;&gt;Sandstorm San Francisco meetup&lt;/a&gt; in January, app author Andrew Wansley shared his story of how his decision to create &amp;amp; package his &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/tr3w5p7ajsf61nf2e6dkfv8tdjes0qsm5w6ew0frd4qwnacwur90&quot;&gt;Giftr&lt;/a&gt; app all started from a simple family tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/tr3w5p7ajsf61nf2e6dkfv8tdjes0qsm5w6ew0frd4qwnacwur90&quot;&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;90%&quot; src=&quot;/news/images/giftr.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;watch-andrews-talk-here&quot;&gt;Watch Andrew’s talk here:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-qIqNXVw4v0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/tr3w5p7ajsf61nf2e6dkfv8tdjes0qsm5w6ew0frd4qwnacwur90&quot;&gt;Giftr&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; remember to review it on the App Market!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-25-giftr</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-25-giftr</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Free publicity for your indie web app, and free Oasis service for you</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Every useful web app deserves users and publicity. Every author deserves an easy way to see their app the way their users see it on Sandstorm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here’s the deal: If you write an open source web app, and you package it for Sandstorm, I’ll help people discover your app and use it. You’ll also get credit toward one year of &lt;a href=&quot;https://oasis.sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oasis managed hosting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; so you can test your app on Sandstorm. The offer applies to anyone who successfully submits an app to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;Sandstorm App Market&lt;/a&gt;, whether or not you’re the original author. It doesn’t have to be open source, though we do love open source. The Oasis hosting can be used for anything you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-sandstorm-package-allows-people-to-use-your-app-even-if-you-dont-maintain-a-public-service&quot;&gt;A Sandstorm package allows people to use your app even if you don’t maintain a public service&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked &lt;a href=&quot;http://simon.vansintjan.net/&quot;&gt;Simon Vansintjan&lt;/a&gt; why he made a Sandstorm package of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/wupmzqk4872vgsye9t9x5dmrdw17mad97dk21jvcm2ph4jataze0&quot;&gt;Quick Survey&lt;/a&gt; app, he told me, “I have no interest in running a SaaS of every small app that I think would be a benefit [to other people].”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simon wants to publish code, not commit to maintaining a service. Simon wrote Quick Survey so he could run one particular survey, as well as for the joy of learning Meteor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By packaging his app for Sandstorm, he got multiple document support without writing any code. Simon said, “Once I understood that [multi-document] translated really well to how Sandstorm views apps / grains, I figured it made a lot of sense to port it to Sandstorm. I’m happy I ended up trying to port it, because it opened up how easy it would be to get other apps up and running with it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/wupmzqk4872vgsye9t9x5dmrdw17mad97dk21jvcm2ph4jataze0&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/2016-02-05-app-author-publicity-oasis/cbd94e8d81ed9bccaf19eb0228dbf451.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/wupmzqk4872vgsye9t9x5dmrdw17mad97dk21jvcm2ph4jataze0&quot;&gt;try out Quick Survey with a click.&lt;/a&gt; Your app could be that easy to spin up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick Survey is a web app that isn’t a business, and Sandstorm is perfect for apps like that. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/frigginglorious&quot;&gt;Daniel Kraft&lt;/a&gt; is nearly done packaging up his personal D&amp;amp;D dice rolling app. What hobby apps have you made that others might enjoy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;publicity-graphics-app-demo-outreach-and-more&quot;&gt;Publicity: Graphics, app demo, outreach, and more&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your app is on the Sandstorm app market, it’s naturally in front of people who use Sandstorm every day. Universities, corporations, non-profits, and self-hosting enthusiasts alike spend huge amounts of time in apps on Sandstorm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, every Sandstorm app is supported by the Sandstorm.io community team — Néna, Jade, and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Néna supports open source web app developers by &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2015-11-10-icons-spks-for-everyone#graphics-for-everyone&quot;&gt;providing graphics&lt;/a&gt; for any app with a Sandstorm package. Here are some of the graphics she’s put together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/2016-02-05-app-author-publicity-oasis/10-appdesigns.png&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three of us spend every day thinking about how to get more people using the apps in the Sandstorm ecosystem. The apps are what what make Sandstorm interesting. So we do things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Give every app a free, live demo service. This one goes to Hacker Slides. It could go to your app. &lt;a href=&quot;https://demo.sandstorm.io/appdemo/7qvcjh7gk0rzdx1s3c8gufd288sesf6vvdt297756xcv4q8xxvhh&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Try Hacker Slides on Sandstorm&quot; src=&quot;/news/images/2016-02-05-app-author-publicity-oasis/try-live%20demo-783189.svg&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 92;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/life/14/8/sandstorm-open-source-web-apps&quot;&gt;Write&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/life/16/1/8-ways-contribute-open-source-without-writing-code&quot;&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/life/15/12/5-open-source-web-apps-self-hosted&quot;&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; outlets like opensource.com, reaching many thousands of readers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write about new apps in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/#join-list&quot;&gt;monthly newsletter&lt;/a&gt;, seen by thousands of subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Encourage Sandstorm community members to &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2015-12-17-community-talks&quot;&gt;give talks&lt;/a&gt; about their favorite apps and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/topics/sandstorm/&quot;&gt;organize meetups.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-01-22-8-new-open-source-apps&quot;&gt;blog posts about new apps&lt;/a&gt;, frequently seen on &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11022993&quot;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; (thanks to Andy for submitting the most recent one!).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find organizations that care about specific apps, and explain to them in person how the community’s apps plus self-hosting it would help the organization achieve its mission.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sandstorm &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/community&quot;&gt;community&lt;/a&gt; as a whole will give you feedback on your app if you email the &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/sandstorm-dev&quot;&gt;sandstorm-dev group&lt;/a&gt;. Check out these &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sandstorm-dev/YNiAzlqON40&quot;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/sandstorm-dev/nVu9VBNFNUM&quot;&gt;threads&lt;/a&gt; to see how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want self-hosting to be a meaningful alternative to software as a service. You can be part of that movement by packaging your app for Sandstorm. If your app is written using Meteor, I’ll even create the &lt;a href=&quot;one-click-installers-for-everyone&quot;&gt;initial packaging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;see-what-users-see-with-a-free-power-user-account-on-oasis&quot;&gt;See what users see, with a free Power User account on Oasis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your users probably don’t know how to deploy your app, which is why they need Sandstorm. I want you to be able to see what your users see, so I’ll give you &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/get&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a free year of Power User level on Oasis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; managed hosting if you write or package an app for Sandstorm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you’re on Oasis, feel free to enjoy it for anything else within the usual terms and conditions. Take advantage of private git repositories with &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/d9ygf47xrtnw12j92cyt6cu8ut75esx01u4q3kcrn8415w9qzzgh&quot;&gt;gogs&lt;/a&gt;, project task tracking with &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/m86q05rdvj14yvn78ghaxynqz7u2svw6rnttptxx49g1785cdv1h&quot;&gt;Wekan&lt;/a&gt;, or privacy-preserving web analytics with &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/xuajusd5d4a9v4js71ru0cwj9wn984q1x8kny10htsp8f5dcfep0&quot;&gt;Piwik&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll also give you an invite to &lt;a href=&quot;https://keybase.io&quot;&gt;Keybase&lt;/a&gt; so when people install your apps, they can verify your identity via the world’s most usable interface to PGP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-get-started-read-the-docs-or-email-me&quot;&gt;To get started, read the docs, or email me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every good web app deserves users and publicity. I’m here to help you with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can dive right in by reading the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/vagrant-spk/packaging-tutorial/&quot;&gt;packaging tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. Sandstorm supports any language/stack that runs on Linux, and has special &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sandstorm.io/en/latest/vagrant-spk/platform-stacks/&quot;&gt;tooling&lt;/a&gt; for nodejs, PHP/MySQL, Meteor, and Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re unsure, or you just want to chat, or you’re waiting on us to publish your app, it’d be my honor to hear from you. Send me an email at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#105;&amp;#111;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#105;&amp;#111;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-05-app-author-publicity-oasis</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-05-app-author-publicity-oasis</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Sandstorm user stories from Hacker News</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-01-22-8-new-open-source-apps&quot;&gt;my previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; was discussed on Hacker News yesterday, &lt;em&gt;andybak&lt;/em&gt; asked to “hear from people that are using Sandstorm day to day.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=11023300&quot;&gt;Reading the replies&lt;/a&gt; really made me appreciate the warmth of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/community&quot;&gt;Sandstorm community&lt;/a&gt;, and I just wanted to share a few excerpts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nolan Darilek writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;notbig&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I use Sandstorm daily. Private/company projects are run in &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/zx9d3pt0fjh4uqrprjftgpqfwgzp6y2ena6098ug3ctv37uv6kfh&quot;&gt;Gitlab&lt;/a&gt; instances, though I may switch to &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/6va4cjamc21j0znf5h5rrgnv0rpyvh1vaxurkrgknefvj0x63ash&quot;&gt;Gitweb&lt;/a&gt; if a minor cosmetic issue is resolved  (Gitweb in Sandstorm can only host one repo by design but you still have to click through to it when viewing the instance, which is mildly annoying when all other apps come up ready to use.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a bunch of &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/m86q05rdvj14yvn78ghaxynqz7u2svw6rnttptxx49g1785cdv1h&quot;&gt;Wekan&lt;/a&gt; boards managing everything from coding projects to my GTD buckets to separate boards for random home improvement projects. I prefer Wekan to spreadsheets because I can track work through arbitrary workflows and annotate items with additional data, and Sandstorm lets me manage that without having to maintain and secure a separate Wekan server that any random person could find and exploit. My blog is hosted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/aax9j672p6z8n7nyupzvj2nmumeqd4upa0f7mgu8gprwmy53x04h&quot;&gt;Sandstorm WordPress&lt;/a&gt; so I have the niceness of its admin interface but none of its security risks, and all the speed of a static site. A small 2-person bootstrapped startup I’ve cofounded uses it for many of the same use cases plus hosting our app’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/xuajusd5d4a9v4js71ru0cwj9wn984q1x8kny10htsp8f5dcfep0&quot;&gt;Piwik&lt;/a&gt; instance, again so there’s literally no non-Sandstorm-secured user-facing attack surface other than Piwik’s API endpoint. I have an idea for a platform co-op in the middle distant future, and if I manage to launch it then I’ll run it via Sandstorm-hosted Loomio, which I’m actively attempting to port and am fairly close to completing.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sandstorm is a great platform, and the community comprises some of the nicest, most dedicated folks I know. When my cofounder messed up our install a bit, Kenton talked us through fixing it on a weekend no less, right down to giving us database queries to run and then patching Sandstorm to handle our edge case the next week. Awesome people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacob Weisz writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;notbig&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I use Sandstorm daily. Effectively it &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/life/15/12/5-open-source-web-apps-self-hosted&quot;&gt;replaces Google Drive/Docs&lt;/a&gt; for me. I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/h37dm17aa89yrd8zuqpdn36p6zntumtv08fjpu8a8zrte7q1cn60&quot;&gt;Etherpad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/a0n6hwm32zjsrzes8gnjg734dh6jwt7x83xdgytspe761pe2asw0&quot;&gt;EtherCalc&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/n4n49dkfyskmhcmg5h0mfzk4kjvce2jcs8ravr7y7uw9xs2pzghh&quot;&gt;Text Editor&lt;/a&gt; a lot on it. And I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8aspz4sfjnp8u89000mh2v1xrdyx97ytn8hq71mdzv4p4d8n0n3h&quot;&gt;Davros&lt;/a&gt; for storing arbitrary files I want to share. My blog is hosted on Sandstorm, but I’ve posted to it like four times so it doesn’t really count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Dee writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;notbig&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’ve been hosting a &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/wfg1r0qra2ewyvns05r0rddqttt57qxurz3nz5z95rjnm63et7e0&quot;&gt;Groove Basin&lt;/a&gt; instance on it for the last little while. Check it out, it’s anarchist radio! &lt;a href=&quot;https://mrdomino.sandcats.io/shared/_NnFzbFzvci0JBgXw3hRwCWOHeECQkJEIO00t2zUmXX&quot;&gt;Link »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;At some point some crazy mofo is going to post it to hackernews. Hopefully I don’t have to revoke the URL and clean up any spam and y’all just groove with the little community I’ve got going on there! But just in case, here’s one where you can only listen, that might last a little longer: &lt;a href=&quot;https://mrdomino.sandcats.io/shared/kYJ-X75DzV3HTB0Ro6cTizCDhUUSyFd3xnNczrxKXbZ&quot;&gt;Link »&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I posted a URL for that station to my work’s Slack, and then people started uploading stuff and rocking out. We’ve had a great time taking turns DJing, sharing our musical taste with each other, and hijacking the stream when it gets too boring or weird. I’ve had friends of mine jump on from elsewhere in the world, some who I haven’t seen in years, and drop their music on us. We’re completely in love with this – it’s a way for us to stay connected through music without disturbing the people who just want to work quietly.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I’m astounded at how easy Sandstorm made this whole thing. These guys continue to blow me away with their ability to create incredibly useful experiences on a small budget and in such a short time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you using Sandstorm at work? Drop me a line at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#105;&amp;#111;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#105;&amp;#111;&lt;/a&gt;, I’d love to hear about it and find out how I can be useful!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-03-hn-highlights</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-02-03-hn-highlights</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>App update: 8 New open source self-hostable apps</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Have an &lt;a href=&quot;http://oasis.sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;Oasis account&lt;/a&gt; already? If not, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/get&quot;&gt;sign up for one right now&lt;/a&gt; and start using it to install any of the 48 apps in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;Sandstorm App Market&lt;/a&gt;. (You can also &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/get#self-hosting&quot;&gt;use your own Linux box&lt;/a&gt;, of course.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;App authors in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandstorm.io/community&quot;&gt;Sandstorm community&lt;/a&gt; have been exceptionally productive lately, packaging their favorite apps and writing original apps as well. I wanted to share some of my recent favorites with you. Here are some brand new apps you should install on your Sandstorm server today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;davros-file-sync&quot;&gt;Davros (file-sync)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8aspz4sfjnp8u89000mh2v1xrdyx97ytn8hq71mdzv4p4d8n0n3h&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/davros-screenshot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Davros screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8aspz4sfjnp8u89000mh2v1xrdyx97ytn8hq71mdzv4p4d8n0n3h&quot;&gt;Davros&lt;/a&gt; is an open source alternative to Dropbox that works with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://owncloud.org/install/#install-clients&quot;&gt;ownCloud client&lt;/a&gt; installed on your local machine. It’s an original app by Michael Nutt (one of the founders of &lt;a href=&quot;https://movableink.com/&quot;&gt;Movable Ink&lt;/a&gt;) who also hosts the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/Sandstorm-NY/&quot;&gt;Sandstorm NY meetup&lt;/a&gt;. He also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/4mfserfc04wtcevvgn0jw27hvwfntmt8j468y3ma55kj8d5tj9kh&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&lt;/a&gt; (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sandforms-forms&quot;&gt;SandForms (forms)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/ztxnreej8a0pqn97ccfhuckswjkrmsaavn85n5sgzk30tv2k4y9h&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/sandforms.png&quot; alt=&quot;SandForms screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/ztxnreej8a0pqn97ccfhuckswjkrmsaavn85n5sgzk30tv2k4y9h&quot;&gt;SandForms&lt;/a&gt; is a slick open source forms app (alternative to Google Forms), by a team at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtworks.com/&quot;&gt;ThoughtWorks&lt;/a&gt;, led by Jack Singleton, who is also author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/7qvcjh7gk0rzdx1s3c8gufd288sesf6vvdt297756xcv4q8xxvhh&quot;&gt;Hacker Slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rocketchat-slack-alternative&quot;&gt;Rocket.Chat (Slack alternative)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/vfnwptfn02ty21w715snyyczw0nqxkv3jvawcah10c6z7hj1hnu0&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rocketchat.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rocket.Chat screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/vfnwptfn02ty21w715snyyczw0nqxkv3jvawcah10c6z7hj1hnu0&quot;&gt;Rocket.Chat&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.okturtles.com/2015/11/five-open-source-slack-alternatives/&quot;&gt;a full-featured open source Slack alternative&lt;/a&gt; that has taken the world by storm (by Gabriel Engel and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rocket.chat&quot;&gt;Rocket.Chat&lt;/a&gt; team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hummingbird-real-time-web-tracker&quot;&gt;Hummingbird (real-time web tracker)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/4mfserfc04wtcevvgn0jw27hvwfntmt8j468y3ma55kj8d5tj9kh&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/06980a0d551bed7ef4eb3991ae1cb92f.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/4mfserfc04wtcevvgn0jw27hvwfntmt8j468y3ma55kj8d5tj9kh&quot;&gt;Hummingbird&lt;/a&gt; gives you real-time web statistics on your website, much like the real-time feature in Google Analytics. It’s also by Michael Nutt (author of &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8aspz4sfjnp8u89000mh2v1xrdyx97ytn8hq71mdzv4p4d8n0n3h&quot;&gt;Davros&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gogs-git-server--interface&quot;&gt;Gogs (git server &amp;amp; interface)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/d9ygf47xrtnw12j92cyt6cu8ut75esx01u4q3kcrn8415w9qzzgh&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/gogs_screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/d9ygf47xrtnw12j92cyt6cu8ut75esx01u4q3kcrn8415w9qzzgh&quot;&gt;Gogs&lt;/a&gt; is an advanced yet lightweight git server that also ships with an issue tracker. It was packaged by Cem Kocagil, who also packaged a bunch of apps I’ll talk about below. (Gog upstream authors: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gogs.io/&quot;&gt;Gogs team&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dillinger-markdown-editor&quot;&gt;Dillinger (markdown editor)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/fq057t4ek3yt96xsfje6c1wv61pkjkqm9hs1539x4jqxjwzdp7fh&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/dillinger_screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/fq057t4ek3yt96xsfje6c1wv61pkjkqm9hs1539x4jqxjwzdp7fh&quot;&gt;Dillinger&lt;/a&gt; is a markdown editor with side-by-side panels, much like desktop markdown editor LightPaper, where the left side is for editing, and the right side is for previews. It was also packaged by Cem Kocagil. (Upstream author: Joe McCann).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nodebb-bulletin-board&quot;&gt;NodeBB (bulletin board)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/zt4j87mc54jkgaehgfqyq2a0qeytm15pcskazvxfkh10yqg4rsrh&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/5f71ba0fe62cc3d437db933495a7c121.png&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/zt4j87mc54jkgaehgfqyq2a0qeytm15pcskazvxfkh10yqg4rsrh&quot;&gt;NodeBB&lt;/a&gt; is a real-time forum app, featuring a modern user interface, tags, voting, and real-time chat. Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/d9ygf47xrtnw12j92cyt6cu8ut75esx01u4q3kcrn8415w9qzzgh&quot;&gt;Gogs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/fq057t4ek3yt96xsfje6c1wv61pkjkqm9hs1539x4jqxjwzdp7fh&quot;&gt;Dillinger&lt;/a&gt;, it was also packaged by Cem Kocagil. (Upstream author: &lt;a href=&quot;https://nodebb.org/&quot;&gt;NodeBB&lt;/a&gt;, Inc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dokuwiki-wiki&quot;&gt;DokuWiki (wiki)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/nx3dqcmz2sjjz939vkg4847vvxrzqsatqfjrt3ea50z3jac5kv7h&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/news/images/DokuWiki_screenshot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DokuWiki is a simple yet versatile classic-style wiki. It was packaged by Nolan Darilek, who also packaged lightweight accounting app &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8x12h6p0x0nrzk73hfq6zh2jxtgyzzcty7qsatkg7jfg2mzw5n90&quot;&gt;HLedger Web&lt;/a&gt;. (Upstream author: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dokuwiki.org&quot;&gt;DokuWiki Team&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-more&quot;&gt;And more…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to share with you an article I wrote for OpenSource.com, highlighting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://opensource.com/life/15/12/5-open-source-web-apps-self-hosted&quot;&gt;open source apps on Sandstorm that replace Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out these apps and more in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.sandstorm.io&quot;&gt;Sandstorm App Market&lt;/a&gt;. Or write your own round-up blog post of your own favorite apps and drop a line to &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#105;&amp;#111;&quot;&gt;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#109;&amp;#117;&amp;#110;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#121;&amp;#064;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#105;&amp;#111;&lt;/a&gt; to let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;spread-the-love&quot;&gt;Spread the love&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that you can get bonus storage on Oasis through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://oasis.sandstorm.io/referrals&quot;&gt;referral program&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlock up to 30GB if you’re a paid user, or up to 2GB bonus storage (+ unlimited grains) for free tier users. (Technically, all plans are free right now while we’re in beta, so catch that while you can.)  That bonus storage will come in handy when you switch over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8aspz4sfjnp8u89000mh2v1xrdyx97ytn8hq71mdzv4p4d8n0n3h&quot;&gt;Davros&lt;/a&gt; like me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
                                <link>https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-01-22-8-new-open-source-apps</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://sandstorm.io/news/2016-01-22-8-new-open-source-apps</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
